Guide to the Mark Hall Amitin/ World of Culture for the Performing Arts, Inc. Archive MSS.121
Fales Library and Special Collections
Mark Hall Amitin/ World of Culture for the Performing Arts, Inc. Archive
1946-2001
Fales Library and Special Collections
Amitin, Mark Hall
MSS.121
120 Linear Feet in 80 boxes
The Mark Hall Amitin/ World of Culture for the Performing Arts, Inc. Archive comprises material collected by Mark Hall Amitin pertaining to his work as a theatrical agent and representative, tour manager, producer, director, writer, lecturer, actor, and founder of Universal Movement Theatre Repertory and World of Culture for the Performing Arts, Inc. Most of the material in the archive dates from the late seventies through the mid-nineties and comprises printed matter, letters, photographs, video and sound recordings, legal and financial documents, journals, technical drawings and notes, and art work. The collection is organized into 9 series contained in 80 boxes, including three oversize boxes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Mark Hall Amitin/ World of Culture for the Performing Arts, Inc. Archive was purchased from Mark Hall Amitin by NYU in 2001. Funds for the purchase were raised by the Fales Library with the assistance of Mark Hall Amitin.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open without restrictions. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Biographical Note
Mark Hall Amitin received his doctoral degree from the Universite Paris VIII in 1978. He went on to present lectures and workshops at universities in the United States, Europe, Canada, and Asia. He worked as a consultant and producer for several major theatre festivals, including the American College Theatre Festival, the Rhode Island Theatre Festival, the Festival Mondial du Theatre in Nancy, France, and the New Theatre Festival in Baltimore. He has published articles on theatre and performance in academic journals and contributed articles and reviews on film and theatre to books, magazines, and newspapers. He has also acted in, and directed, film, television, and theatre projects in the United States as well as in the Middle East, Europe, and Asia.
Amitin was manager of the Radical Theatre Repertory, which later became Universal Movement Theatre Repertory, a non-profit agency representing experimental theatre companies from the United States and Europe. He was also the producer of Albee Directs Albee (1978-1979) and touring manager for The Living Theatre. Amitin travelled extensively in the Middle East, Asia, and Europe and helped to establish relations between theatre groups and individual artists from various countries.
In 1981 Amitin founded the World of Culture, Ltd. (later the non-profit World of Culture for the Performing Arts, Inc.) in order to represent theatrical groups and individual film, television, and theatre actors, writers, designers, and directors, and to establish a network that would facilitate touring and performing worldwide. He also worked as a writer, researcher, consultant, and director on several film and television projects including the film Signals Through the Flames(1982-1983) and the television miniseries about Agnes Smedley, The Eyes of a Friend(1985-1986). Amitin's involvement in festivals such as The New Theatre Festival in Baltimore and the Festival Mondial du Theatre de Nancy allowed him to become familiar with many theatrical groups and collectives and to faciliate their introduction to audiences outside of their own countries. He shared the political aspirations of many of these groups and worked vigorously to secure their representation in different venues.
Amitin was keenly interested in the craft of acting and taught many workshops on the practical aspects of acting and auditioning at colleges and universities. He also lectured in universities around the world on topics such as twentieth-century theatre in China, politics and theatre in the United States, the work of The Living Theatre and other collectives, and theatre of the avant-garde. He helped to negotiate theatre, film, and television contracts, working with Broadway shows, institutions such as the Lincoln Center, and directors such as Woody Allen, Francis Ford Coppola, Martin Scorsese, Mike Nichols, Penny Marshall, Roland Jaffe, and Jim Jarmusch.
Scope and Content Note
The collection is divided into 9 series, beginning with the series "Personal Collection," which has 10 subseries. There is some overlap between this series and the other series but material in the first pertains mostly to Amitin's personal business and to non-Universal Movement Theatre Repertory (UMTR) and non-World of Culture (WOC) business. Some individuals and groups were represented both by UMTR and by WOC, and thus material on them may be found in both the UMTR and the WOC series (e.g. Squat Theatre).
The materials in this collection make an important contribution to the representation of avant-garde performing and theatrical arts from the nineteen seventies through the early nineteen nineties. Mark Amitin participated in and represented several key avant-garde performing arts groups of this period, helping them to make contacts in other countries, to perform at important theatre festivals in the United States and Europe, and to secure funding for tours abroad and at home. He worked closely with such writers and directors as Edward Albee, Joseph Chaikin, and Jean-Claude van Itallie, helping to produce tours and individual performances at venues all over the world.
The collection will be of interest to anyone doing research on avant-garde theatre and performance art of the late twentieth-century. It includes material on groups such as The Living Theatre, The San Francisco Mime Troupe, The Bread and Puppet Theatre, The Kipper Kids, Le Plan K, and Teatro Campesino, and on individuals such as Judith Malina, Julian Beck, Steve Buscemi, Peter Facinelli, Joseph Chaikin, Jean-Claude van Itallie, Franne Lee, Shirley Stoler and Paul Zaloom.
It will also prove useful to researchers interested in the day to day functioning of a theatrical agency since it includes correspondence with clients, contracts, details of touring and theatre productions, flyers, brochures, and personal notes. The collection forms part of the Fales Library's growing collection of twentieth-century performance related archives that includes the papers of the Judson Dance Theater and Judson Poets Theater in the Judson Memorial Church Archive, the Papers of Laura Foreman, the Robert Alexander Papers, the Mabou Mines Archive, and the Richard Foreman Papers.
SERIES I: Personal Papers
Materials in this series pertain to Amitin's work as an agent, actor, writer, tour manager, and teacher. The series comprises correspondence, brochures, notes, flyers, legal documents, scripts, screenplays, playbills, and personal memorabilia collected over a thirty-year period. There may be some overlap with other series but in general the material in this series concerns business not directly related to Universal Movement Theatre Repertory (UMTR) or World of Culture (WOC).
Subseries A: Middle East
Includes brochures, correspondence, announcements, programs, and notes pertaining to theatre in Israel, Palestine, and Egypt.
Subseries B: China
Comprises material collected during visits to China, including brochures, flyers, and programs. Also includes Amitin's correspondence with actors, writers, directors, and theatre groups in China.
Subseries C: Albee Directs Albee
Includes material pertaining to Amitin's production of Edward Albee's tour of one-act plays in 1978 and 1979.
Subseries D: Scripts and Screenplays
Organized alphabetically by writer.
Subseries E: Playbills, Programs, Flyers, Brochures
Organized by production name with the director's name in parentheses, except in cases where there are several items pertaining to the same director (usually Amitin clients). Researchers should look first under production name and then, failing that, under director name.
Subseries F: Professional Writing
Includes interview notes and transcripts, reviews, articles, and drafts and final versions of essays by Mark Amitin for magazines, newspapers, and academic journals.
Subseries G: Dissertation, Datebooks, Journals
Includes Amitin's notes for, and drafts of, his Ph.D. dissertation and his journals (organized chronologically).
Subseries H: Personal Correspondence
Researchers will see 4 tiers of organization in this subseries: 1) entire names, in alphabetical order, with several letters to a folder; 2) lettered folders for last names with several letters to a folder; 3) lettered folders for first names with several letters to a folder; 4) unidentified correspondents. There is also one box of unsorted cards and postcards.
Subseries I: Business files, theatre companies, flyers, general correspondence
SERIES II: Universal Movement Theatre Repertory (UMTR)
Material in this series includes correspondence, financial records, flyers, playbills, brochures, CVs, and general business documents.
SERIES III: The Living Theatre
Mark Hall Amitin was associated with The Living Theatre from the mid-1960's. He was their touring manager from 1968-1969 and their General Manager in 1984. Materials in this series document The Living Theatre productions and activities from this period and include brochures, correspondence, flyers, posters, scripts, interviews, press clippings, handwritten production notes, and journals. This series covers the period of Amitin's management of the Living Theatre but also contains archival material dating from prior to and after this period. Materials on Judith Malina and Julian Beck not pertaining directly to their involvement with The Living Theatre have been collected in the World of Culture series (since Amitin represented them individually as well as in their capacity as founders of The Living Theatre).
SERIES IV: World of Culture (WOC)
In 1981 Amitin founded World of Culture Ltd. as an arts agency and consultancy for theatre, film, and television. He represented actors, directors, designers, and writers. In 1996, he founded the non-profit organization called World of Culture for the Performing Arts, Inc. to facilitate international cultural exchange in performance and the arts. Materials in this series pertain to both organizations.
SERIES V: Video
Contains all videorecordings. Material is separated into two subseries. Researcher access is limited to Subseries A: Access Copies. Subseries B: Originals consists of all videorecordings in the collcection. Access copies may not be available for all material yet.
Subseries A: Access Copies
Organized chronologically. Please check with a Fales Archivist.
Subseries B: Originals
Organized alphabetically by subject. Access copies may not be available yet. Please check with the Fales Archivist.
SERIES VI: Audio
Contains all audiorecordings. Material is separated into two subseries. Researcher access is limited to Subseries A: Access Copies. Subseries B: Originals consists of all audiorecordings in the collcection. Access copies may not be available for all material yet.
Subseries A: Access Copies
Organized chronologically. Please check with a Fales Archivist.
Subseries B: Originals
Organized alphabetically by subject. Access copies may not be available yet. Please check with the Fales Archivist.
SERIES VII: Photographs and Slides
Organized alphabetically by subject.
SERIES VIII: Posters
Organized alphabetically by company or director name.
SERIES IX: Printed Matter
One box of magazines/ newspapers with articles by Amitin or reviews/ articles on Amitin clients. Alphabetized but not foldered.
Arrangement
Materials in each series are organized alphabetically and chronologically. For personal correspondence in Series I, Subseries H, each correspondent has been allotted a single folder, except when there is only one letter from a correspondent. In the latter case, several letters from different correspondents may be found in one folder, organized alphabetically.
Missing Title
Series I: Personal Papers
Series II: Universal Movement Theatre Repertory
Series III: The Living Theatre
Series IV: World of Culture
Series V: Videorecordings
Series VI: Audio
Series VII: Photographs and Slides
Series VIII: Posters
Series IX: Printed Matter
Related Material at Fales Library and Special Collections
Robert Alexander Papers (MSS.114)
Judson Memorial Church Archive (MSS.094)
Mabou Mines Archive (MSS.133)
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access copies for some materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Theater -- Production and direction.; Videocassettes.; Résumés (personnel records); Actors; Acting; Poetry.; Experimental theater; Postcards.; Israel.; Contracts; China; Notes.; Printed ephemera.; Palestine.; Slides (photographs); Magazines (Periodicals); Theater |z Egypt.; Posters.; Theater |z Palestine.; Theater |z Israel.; Audiocassettes.; Bank statements.; Theater |z China.; Theater and Society.; Audiotapes.; Street theater.; Repertory theater.; Correspondence.; Playbills.; Fliers (printed matter); Negatives (photographic); Photographs.; Financial records; Diaries; Drawings; Tax records.; Scripts (documents); Contact sheets.; Press releases.; New York (N.Y.).; Manuscripts for publication.; Clippings (information artifacts); Books.; Reviews (document genre); Facinelli, Peter, 1973-; Lee, Franne, 1941-; Le Plan K; Beck, Julian, 1925-1985; Chaikin, Joseph, 1935-; Buscemi, Steve, 1958-; Albee, Edward, 1928- 2016; Zaloom, Paul; World of Culture for the Performing Arts, Inc.; World of Culture, Ltd; Universal Movement Theater Repertory; Van Itallie, Jean Claude, 1936-; Stoler, Shirley; Teatro Campesino (Organization); San Francisco Mime Troupe; Bread and Puppet Theater; Squat Theatre (Theater group); Living Theatre (New York, N.Y.); Kipper Kids (Group of artists); Malina, Judith, 1926-
- Series I: Personal Papers
  - Subseries A: Middle East
    - American Cultural Center., 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General
      Offsite Barcode: 31142040617964
    - American Embassy, Tel Aviv., 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Amitin festival workshop flyers., undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Amitin lecture announcements., undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Amitin travel and accommodation., 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Arad Arts Project., undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Ashtar., undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Audition sheet., undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Beit Hagefen Arab Jewish Cultural Centre, Haifa., 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Cameri Theatre., undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Contacts and documentation., undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence: Gad Kaynar, June 21, 1995- February 17, 1997., 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence: Ministry of Culture, January 10, 1994-December 20, 1997., 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence: personal, December 28, 1995-April 18, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence: personal, April 19, 1995- May 24, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence: personal, May 27, 1995-March 25, 1997., 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence: theatre in China., 1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Creative Arts Team - New York University., 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Egypt., undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Gesher Theatre., undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Habama Theatre., undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Haifa University., undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Handwritten notes, Israel., 1993-1997 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Havakuk Neighborhood., undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Hebrew University - lectures, correspondence., 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - International Theatre Institute - Israel Center., 1993-1997 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Israel - cultural information., 1993 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Israeli libraries/ books on theatre in English., undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Israeli press clippings., 1995 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Israeli press on Mark Hall Amitin., 1995 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Israeli theatre - programs., 1995 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Zohar Jacobson., 1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Jerusalem Khan Theatre., undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Middle East - general information, press clippings., 1998 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Roy Nathanson/ "Wasserman"., 1993 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Notes., undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Palestinian National Theatre and other Palestinian theatres., 1994 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - The Perez Institute., 1997 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Playbills, theatre programs., 1994 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - The Room Theatre., undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - School of Visual Theatre., 1994 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - State Teachers College, Tel Aviv., 1994 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Students - Seminar Hakibbutzim., 1995 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Tel Aviv University., 1995 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Tel Aviv University lectures, May 5, 1995 - May 12, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Telephone bills, faxes., 1995 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Video listings., undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Subseries B: China
    - Mark Hall Amitin articles on Chinese theatre - drafts., undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Offsite Barcode: 31142040617972
    - Amitin notebook - teaching proposal., undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Mark Hall Amitin, "Chinese Theatre in Flux"., undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Mark Hall Amitin, "Theatre in China: Beyond the Great Wall"., undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Mark Hall Amitin, "The Theatre of China: An Inside View" - drafts and originals., undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Mark Hall Amitin, "The Theatre of China: An Inside View" - drafts and originals., 1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Mark Hall Amitin, "The Theatre of China: An Inside View" and introduction to Teahouse., undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Association of Chinese Studies., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Beyond the Great Wall" series outline, June 11, 1980. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Bright Eyes - drafts., 1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Bright Eyes - drafts, scene changes., undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Bright Eyes - episode one, drafts, changes., undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Bright Eyes - script., undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Evans Carlson material., undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Center for United States - People's Republic of China Arts Exchange at Columbia University., undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Ai-Li Sung Chin - correspondence and article on China., 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Ai-Li Sung Chin and Shen Cheng Zhou., 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - China - brochures, correspondence, notes., 1980-1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - China - brochures, correspondence, press clippings., 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - China and Hong Kong - notes, correspondence., 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - China and Japan., 1984 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - China press clippings., 1979-1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - China tours correspondence, notes, brochures., 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Chinese film., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Chinese Theatre Arts Tour, June 1987. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Chinese Theatre Association., undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Committee on Scholarly Exchange with the People's Republic of China., 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence., 1973-1980 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence., 1983 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence., 1984 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence., 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence., undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence: Carroll R. Bogert., 1985 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence: Jian Chen., 1986-1990 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence: Claire Conceison., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence: Tsolin Huang., 1979-1986 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence: Ying Ro-Cheng., 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence: Xie Rong Jin., 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence: Liu Si Ping., 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence: Lucy Zhang., 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Documentary proposal., undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Offsite Barcode: 31142040617980
    - Eugene O'Neill Theater Center., 1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - The Eyes of a Friend- script, travel arrangements., 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Grant application., 1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Interview transcripts July 5, 1979. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Life Magazine with Edgar Snow article, July 30, 1971. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - "Mao Danced: Agnes Smedley in China"., 1995 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Memorabilia., undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Joyce Milton, "A Friend of China" (photocopy with marginalia)., 1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Minneapolis China Group., 1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - National Committee on United States - China Relations., 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - New Dramatists Theatre., 1983 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - New Dramatists and Chinese Theatre Association., 1983 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - New Dramatists proposal for an exchange of playwrights with the People's Republic of China., 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Peking Opera., 1980 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Proposal for book on China., 1980 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Research material on China and Chinese theatre., 1972-1984 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Xi She, August 1986. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Agnes Smedley/ "A Friend's Eyes" script, August 1986. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Agnes Smedley in China., 1994 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Agnes Smedley research material., 1980- (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Agnes Smedley script., undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Agnes Smedley script - episode 1, July 28, 1985. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Hu Song - press clippings, copies of diplomas., 1980-1986 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - SUNY Buffalo China conference., Oct 1984 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Teaching in China., 1984 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Theatre brochures., 1979-1984 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - "Theatre in China" - Amitin lecture, November 15, 1979. (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - "Theatre in China" - notes for article., undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - "Theatre in China" - notes, draft., undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - "Theatre in China" - technical information, press releases., 1980 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Travel notes, press clippings., 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Travel receipts., 1983 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - US-China Arts Exchange., 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Cao Yu, "Peking Man"., 1980 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Subseries C: Albee Directs Albee
    - Actors' contracts., 1979 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Offsite Barcode: 31142040617998
    - Actors' photos and resumes., 1978 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Actor questionnaires, July 1978. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Actor questionnaires, July 1978. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Albee's paragraphs for Zoo Story, American Dream, Counting the Ways., undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - The American Dream- script (photocopy)., undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Cast and crew biographies - originals and edited versions., undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Casting announcements, July 1978. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Contracts., 1978 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Contracts., 1978 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Contracts and correspondence., 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Contracts and correspondence., 1977-1979 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Contracts and correspondence., 1977-1979 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Contracts and correspondence., 1977-1979 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Contracts and correspondence., 1977-1979 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Contracts and correspondence., 1977-1979 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Contracts and correspondence: A.C.T., San Francisco., 1978 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Contracts and correspondence: Columbia University., 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Contracts and correspondence: Hong Kong., 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Contracts and correspondence: Japan., 1979 (Box 4, Folder 20)